Guide to the Lourdes Benería papers, 1974-2008.
Benería, Lourdes papers
- 1997 UNDP Human Development Report Advisory Panel, 1997-1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Correspondence related to the 1997 UNDP Poverty and Human Development Report and the Advisory Panel Meeting.
  Annotated Outline of the 1997 UNDP Report. Revision notes on the Draft of the 1997 UNDP Report.
- Radcliffe Public Policy Institute Fellowship, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Correspondence related to appointment as a Radcliffe College Public Policy Fellow (July 1, 1996-June 30, 1997).
  Orientation Schedule for Fellows, Address List of Fellows and Visiting Professor, RPPI Staff Phone List.
  "Brief Description of Research Plans for Fellowship Year."
  "Project Description" (From the MacArthur Proposal).
  Radcliffe Public Policy Institute Policy Seminar Series Pamphlet 1997-1998, and other publications from RPPI.
  Meeting Notes.
- UN Workshop - World Survey on the Role of Women in Development, Geneva, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  List of workshop participants and contact information.
  Correspondence regarding reimbursement for travel expenses.
  Working Draft "Chapter III. Major World Trends, Section D. Migration: aspects of labour mobility" prepared by the International Research and Training Insititute for the Advancement of Women (INSTRAW).
- University of Rochester Conference - Forum 98: Setting a Course for Women into the 21st Century, Seneca Falls, New York, 1998., 1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Correspondence regarding participation in the conference "Forum 98: Setting a Course for Women into the 21st Century" organized by the University of Rochester and Hobart and William Smith Colleges with major funding from the Ford Foundation and others.
  Conference Brochure and Program.
  Handwritten notes for lecture given on July 15, 1998.
  Xerox "Figure 4.2 - Most of women's work remains unpaid, unrecognized and undervalued. SNA and non-SNA work."
  Xerox from UN Human Development Report 1995 "Table A2.3 - Women and Economic Opportunities." Copy of newspaper article from the Rochester Democrat and Chronicle "The Cradle Rocks: Birthplace of Women's Rights Prepares for big year."
  Copies of the Declaration of Sentiments and Declaration of Sentiments reaffirmation statement.
  Copy of Universal Declaration of Human Rights
  Copy of "The Three State Strategy for ERA Ammendment - Summary"
- World Bank Workshop - "Gender and Development," Washington, D.C., April 2-3, 1998, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Correspondence related to participation in the World Bank Workshop "Gender and Development."
  Workshop Agenda.
  Summary of presentation given in the panel discussion with revision notes and final version.
- CUNY Conference - "Which Way for Women and Development? Debating Concepts, Strategies and Directions for the 21st Century," NYC, October 15-17, 1998, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Correspondence related to participation in the conference "Which Way for Women and Development? Debating Concepts, Strategies and Directions for the 21st Century."
  Conference Program.
  Documents: Conference Proposal and Proposed Panels.
- Book "Gender and Development: Theoretical, Empirical and Practical Approaches", 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Correspondence with Edward Elgar Publishing relating to "Gender and Development: Theoretical, Empirical and Practical Approaches."
  Proposed Chapters and Contributors.
  Editor's Promotion Form.
  Publishing Contracts.
- World Bank, ABCDE Conference, Paris, France, 1999, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Correspondence and documents related to participation in the "Annual Bank Conference on Development Economics (ABCDE)."
  Registration form, draft conference program and draft agenda.
- PROMEC Conference "Capitalismo Hoy: Exploraciones Criticas en America Latina y el Mundo," Cochabamba, Bolivia, 1999, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Correspondence and documents related to participation in the PROMEC (Proyesto de Mejoramiento de Formacion en Economia) conference "Capitalismo Hoy: Exploraciones Criticas en America Latina y el Mundo" (in Spanish).
  Conference Program and handwritten notes (in Spanish).
- University of Illinois - "WID Symposium 2000: Women, Gender, and Development - Risks and Rights in the 21st Century," Illinois, 2000, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Correspondence and documents related to participation in the University of Illinois Conference "WID Symposium 2000: Women, Gender, and Development - Risks and Rights in the 21st Century."
  Conference program.
  Lecture flyer for "Changing Employment Structures and Economic Insecurity."
- ILO Meeting of the International Advisory Board of the Socio-Economic Programme, Bellagio, Italy, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Correspondence related to participation in International Labour Organisation's International Advisory Board of the Socio-Economic Programme.
  Meeting agenda and outline of program.
  Overhead projector slides "Unemployment Rate" and "Educational Opportunity" and "Income Before and After - Smith Corona Workers."
  Handwritten lecture notes.
  Preliminary draft copy of paper "Gender Dimensions of Socio-Economic In/Security," written for the meeting of the ILO's International Advisory Board of the Socio-Economic Programme.
- UN - Committee for Development Policy, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Correspondence related to appointment to and member of the UN Economic and Social Council's Committee for Development Policy.
  Meeting documents.
  Biographical information on the nominees for appointment to the Committee for Development Policy.
  Document "Issues Note - Round Table- New York- 14 February 2002- ECOSOC High-Level Segment 2002 - The Contribution of Human Resources Development: Including the areas of health and education, to the process of development."
  Publications from the UN Economic and Social Council Commission on the Status of Women: Discrimination against women and girls in Afghanistan and Implications of the reforms of mechanisms in the human rights area for communications concerning the status of women.
  Annotated Agenda and Programme of Work: Financing Global Social Development Symposium, New York, 7 February, 2002.
- ILO Meeting of the Infocus Programme on Socio-Economic Security - International Advisory Board, Bellagio, Italy, 2001., 2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Correspondence and documents regarding participation in the ILO Meeting of the Infocus Programme on Socio-Economic Security - International Advisory Board, Bellagio, Italy, 2001.
- Cornell University Conference "Rethinking Labor Market Formalization," Ithaca, New York, October 2002, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Correspondence and documents related to organizing the Cornell University Conference "Rethinking Labor Market Formalization; Poverty, Precarious Jobs and Social Protection," Ithaca, New York, October 2002.
  Table of Contents and Contributors for Related Publication.
  ILO Document "Decent Work and the Informal Economy" by Lin Lean Lim.
  Paper "Rethinking Labour Market Informalization: Precarious Jobs, Poverty and Social Protection" by John Langmore.
  One page document regarding the potential closure of the college and redistribution of the departments within Cornell University's College of Architecture, Art and Planning.
- Institut für Stadt- und Regionalforschung (ISR) Conference "Globalization and Urban Studies: How to study the metropolis in transition?" Vienna, Conference, October 2002, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Correspondence related to participation in the Institut für Stadt- und Regionalforschung (ISR) Conference "Globalization and Urban Studies: How to study the metropolis in transition?" Vienna, Conference, October 2002
  Abstract "Labor Market Informalization and the Changing Landscapes of Cities" by Lourdes Benería and Susanna Schaller.
  Conference document containing abstracts from all of the participants.
- DAW Working Group Session at "Day of Dialogue on Gender and Financing for Development", New York, February 25, 2002, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Correspondence and documents related to participation in the DAW Working Group Session at "Day of Dialogue on Gender and Financing for Development", New York, February 25, 2002
  Publication of the UN Economic and Social Council "Thematic issues before the Commission on the Status of Women," 3 January 2002.
  "Aide Memoire" for the Day of Dialogue.
  Document "What kind of development should be financed?" by Cecilia Lopez Montaño, Alma Espino, and Rosalba Todaro, 2001. Excerpt: "This document was written as a reaction to the absence of gender perspective in the Financing for Development Conference debates and preparatory documents."
- UNIFEM Conference "Gender and Trade in the Context of Financing for Development," Monterrey, Mexico, 2002, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Correspondence related to participation in the UNIFEM-UNDP-UNCTAD Conference "Gender and Trade in the Context of Financing for Development," at the International Conference on Financing for Development, Monterrey, Mexico, 2002.
  Excerpt from correspondence sent to Lourdes Benería related to the International Conference on Financing for Development:
  "'...the UN will be eaten for breakfast by the Bretton Woods institutions... this is, in reality, the transnational corporate agenda in drag.'"
  Proposal for the UNIFEM-UNDP-UNCTAD Conference "Gender and Trade in the Context of Financing for Development" at the International Conference on Financing for Development.
  Conference schedule (in Spanish and in English) for the International Conference on Financing for Development.
  Document "Remarks by Hon. Trevor Manuel at the Conference."
  Document "Linking Doha, Monterrey and Johannesburg: A global deal to eradicate poverty and inequality and promote sustainable development."
  Document "Statement of Concern" - Issued by Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN), International Gender and Trade Network (IGTN), Cartagena Feminist Initiative, Red de Educacion Popular Entre Mujeres (REPEM), and endorsed by the Women's Caucus. The "Statement of Concern" documents the isolation and disregard for the perspective of civil society organizations during the International Conference on Financing for Development. Excerpt: "Time has almost run out for this conference to make a real differenc in realizing the MDGs [Millenium Develompent Goals] within a Human Rights Framework."
- Universal Forum of Cultures Conference "Vivir y Convivir: Forum Mundial de las Mujeres," Barcelona, Spain, July, 2004, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Correspondence (in Catalan and Spanish) related to participation in the Universal Forum of Cultures Conference "Vivir y Convivir: Forum Mundial de las Mujeres," Barcelona, Spain, July, 2004.
  Conference Schedule.
  Document "El Treball No Remunerat: Historia d'un Projecte de Contabilitzacio" (in Catalan) with handwritten edits (in Catalan).
  Figures and Tables regarding the relationship between the formal and informal economy and women's work.
- Report for Institute de la Mujer (INAM): "Diagnostico de Genero de Honduras: Aspectos Economicos", 2005 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Paper "Diagnostico de Genero de Honduras: Aspectos Economicos," (in Spanish) Institute de la Mujer, Honduras, July 2005.
- WS360 "Street Stories: Bosnia", VHS Tape (Box 1)
  VHS Video of a broadcast of the CBS News magazine "Street Stories" with Peter Van Sant. This episode is recorded in Bosnia. He interviews war victims and a war criminal.
  "Used in a course."- written on an attached note.
- 1990 Elections Nicaragua (Box 1, 2)
  "Member of delegation (organized by Hemisphere Initiatives) to observe the 1990 Nicaraguan elections in which the Sandinistas lost." -A note from Lourdes Benería.
  - "Food Systems Monograph: A Preliminary Analysis of the Nicaraguan Food System - A progress report of research being carried out under UNRISD's project 'Food Systems and Society,'", 1982 (Box 1)
    Book by Solon Barraclough.
  - "Yo fui un Contra: Historia de un 'Paladín de la Libertad'", 1987 (Box 1)
    Book (in Spanish) by Elizabeth Reimann.
  - "What Difference Could a Revolution Make?- Food and Farming in the New Nicaragua", 1982 (Box 1)
    Book by Joseph Collins.
  - "Sobre La Insurreccion", 1981 (Box 1)
    Book (in Spanish) by Humberto Ortega Saavedra.
  - "Mujer y Agroexportación en Nicaragua", 1987 (Box 1)
    Book (in Spanish) edited by Instituto Nicaraguense de la Mujer.
  - "Carlos, El Amanecer ya no es una Tentacion", 1980 (Box 1)
    Book (in Spanish) by Tomás Borge, Serie Testimonio - Coleccion Nuestros Paises - Casa de las Americas.
  - "Construccion de la Democracia en Nicaragua", 1989 (Box 1)
    Book (in Spanish) by the Escuela de Sociología Universidad Cenrtroamericana.
  - "La Economia Mixta en Nicaragua: Proyecto o Realidad - Una Vision de Academicos y Politicos Nacionales", 1986 (Box 1)
    Book (in Spanish) by the Centro de Investigacion y Asesoria Socio-Economica y Fundacion Friedrich Ebert Stiftung.
  - "El FSLN y la Mujer en la Revolución Popular Sandinista", 1987 (Box 1)
    Publication (in Spanish) by Dirrección Nacional Frent Sandinista de Liberación Nacional and published by Editorial Vanguardia.
  - "Revista Nicaraguense de Ciencias Sociales", 1987 (Box 1)
    Publication (in Spanish) de la Asociacion Nicaraguense de Clientificos Sociales, Ano 2 - No. 2.
  - "Cuadernos de Investigacion 1", 1987 (Box 1)
    Publication (in Spanish) - Includes articles on "El concepto de productividad," "Crisis alimentaria y participacion popular," "Las vendedoras de los mercados."
  - "Informes: 10 Anos de Investigaciones Sobre la Mujer en Nicaragua 1976-1986", 1986 (Box 1)
    Publication (in Spanish) by the Oficina de la Mujer, Ministerio de la Presidencia, 1986.
  - "Informe: Inventario de Proyectos para la Mujer en Nicaragua", 1987 (Box 1)
    Publication (in Spanish) by the Oficina de la Mujer, Ministerio de la Presidencia, 1987.
  - "Realidad y Perspectiva: Bibliografia nacional anotada sobre la Mujer en Nicaragua", 1987 (Box 1)
  - Nicaragua: Newspaper Articles by and about Lourdes Benería, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Clippings and photocopies of newspaper articles about the Nicaraguan Elections by or about Lourdes Benería. In Spanish and in English.
  - Nicaragua: Women, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Journal, book and newspaper articles about Nicaraguan women.
    "Women in Nicaragua" by Beth Stevens, 1988.
    "La rebeldia de las mujeres nicaragüenses: semillero de una nueva democracia" (in Spanish) by Ana Criquillion, 1989.
    "Mujer y Derechos Politicos" (in Spanish) by Milu Vargas Escobar, 1989.
    "Mujer y Partidos Políticos" (in Spanish) by Patricia Vargas Fernandez, Milu Vargas Escobar, and Josefina Ramos Mendoza.
    "The Situation of Women in Nicaragua" by Malena de Montis and Mercedes Olivera for El Centro De Investigacion y Accion Participative (CIAP), 1989.
  - Nicaragua: UNO and FSLN Platforms, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Newsprint pamphlets. "Programa de Govierno de la Unión Nacional Opositora UNO" (Union Nacional Opositora) (in Spanish).
    "Frente Sandinista de Liberacion Nacional (FSLN) Plataforma Electoral (1990-1997) !Todo Sera Mejor!" (in Spanish).
  - Nicaragua: Newspaper Clippings, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Newspaper clippings (in Spanish and English) from NYTimes, la Semana Comica ("Semanario de Humor Marxismo Sexo y Violencia"), the Guardian ("Independant Radical Newsweekly").
  - Nicaragua: Economia - Newspaper Clippings, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Newspaper clippings (in Spanish and English) NYTimes, La Cronica ("Por una socieddad mas justa, mas amplia, mas generosa"), La Prensa, and Barracida.
  - Nicaragua: Travel Documents, Notes, Papers, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Copy of paper "Nicaragua: Elecciones/90" (in Spanish) by Lourdes Benería (1990) and publication request letter (in Spanish) dated February 19, 1990 to Sr. Angel Harguindey, Seccion de Colaboraciones, El Pais, Madrid, Spain.
    Handwritten notes for lecture given at the CUSLAR Sister City Event, 1st Unitarian Church, February 22, 1990.
    Bright orange, wire-bound, college ruled notebook containing hand written notes, names and addresses (in Spanish).
    Correspondence related to the Hemisphere Initiatives.
    Travel agenda, plane tickets, financial documentation, map of Nicaragua, newspaper clippings (in Spanish). Document "Latin American Studies Association Delegation to Observe the February 25, 1990 Nicaraguan Election, Interim Report, December 4, 1989."
  - Nicaragua: Economics - Papers and Publications, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Background Paper on Nicaraguan Economy and Politics from Hemisphere Initiatives.
    Journal: "Análisis - Revista Económica de Nicaragua - Computación - ?Hacia Dónde va Nicaragua?" No. 4 Diciembre 1989, Managua, Nicaragua.
    Journal: "Análisis - Revista Económica de Nicaragua - ?Inflación bajo control?" No. 1 Agosto 1989, Managua, Nicaragua.
  - Nicaragua: Hemisphere Initiatives Documents, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Document "Establishing the Ground Rules: A Report on the Nicaraguan Electoral Process: August, 1989" by Hemisphere Initiatives, Boston, Massachusetts.
    Hemisphere Initiatives Pamphlets, Correspondence regarding participation in the monitoring process.
    Article "The Nicaraguan Elections: Observations Based Upon the January HI Delegation" by David Samuel Krusé, 1990.
    Article/Letter from Dennis Gilbert about his impressions, 1990.
    Article "Why the Sandinistas are Winning the Election" by David Samuel Krusé.
    Article "Panama Invasion Gives Sandinistas Decisive Lead in Elections" by Elizabeth Dore, 1990.
  - Nicaragua: Election Publications and Rules, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Booklet "Electoral Law and Reforms" by the Supreme Electoral Council.
    Electoral Supreme Council Bulletin Number 1 Managua, Nicaragua, July-August-1989.
    Electoral Supreme Council Bulletin Number 2 Managua, Nicaragua, July-1989.
    "Rules for processing foreign donations to political parties, alliances of parties or petitioning associations." (in Spanish and English) Consejo Supremo Electoral Boletín Informativo Managua, Nicaragua, Noviembre de 1989.
    "Procedures for the filing of complaints or accusations:"(in Spanish and English) Consejo Supremo Electoral Boletín Informativo Managua, Nicaragua, Noviembre de 1989.
    "Rules of Electoral Ethics" Supreme Electoral Council Bulletin Managua, Nicaragua, October 1989.
    "Regulation on International Observation of the Electoral Process" Supreme Electoral Council Bulletin Managua, Nicaragua, October 1989.
    Newsprint Booklet "Manual de Educación Cívica y Capacitación Electoral No. 2 Votacion y Escrutinio" (in Spanish) Consejo Supremo Electoral.
    Pamphlet "Minstructivo Sobre las Funciones de los Fiscales" Consejo Supremo Electoral.
    Newprint booklet "Plataforma Electoral del FSLN (1990-1997) !Todo Será Mejor! - el 25 en la 5" (in Spanish).
  - Nicaragua: Newsletters, Papers, Reports, Articles, 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Article "The CIA's Blueprint for Nicaragua" by Philip Agee in CoverntAction, Number 6 (October 1979).
    Newletter #12 from Mardy Townsend of "Clergy and Laity Concerned," Nicaragua, November 12, 1990.
    News Release "Hotline - Witness for Peace," October 20, 1989.
    News Release "Hotline - Witness for Peace," November 16, 1989.
    News Release "Hotline - Witness for Peace," January 11, 1990.
    Book Excerpt "Chapter 4: Nicaragua" from Confronting Revolution: Security Through Diplomacy in Central America.
    Document of Alejandro Bendana, Secretary General Nicaragua Foreign Ministry, Talk before a meeting of Nicaragua solidarity activists, 25 March, 1990.
    Article "Clase, Estado y Etnicidad en las Costa Atlantica de Nicaragua" by Carlos M. Vilas, 1989 for a Panel on Democacy and Popular Participation in Nicaragua.
    Article "Plan Basico de Gobierno - Partido Social Cristiano Nicaraguense (PSC) - La Alternativa Cristiana" by Erick Ramirez Penavente, Managua, Nicaragua.
    "Report of an Economic Mission to the Government of Nicaragua" (marked "Confidential - Not for quotation") by D. Kruse, 5 April, 1989.